<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Presbyterian Music Camp</title>
    <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website" />
    <updated>2020-02-17T19:03:13-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Thanks for registering!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/thanks-for-registering.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/thanks-for-registering.html</id>

        <updated>2020-02-17T19:01:26-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    See you soon!
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="align-center">See you soon!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/frequently-asked-questions.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/frequently-asked-questions.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-17T18:50:25-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    FoodAre all of my meals and snacks included? For the most part, yes! Your camper&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="mcetoc_1duqtp0m27"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Food</span></h2>
<p><strong>Are all of my meals and snacks included?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> For the most part, yes! Your camper fees include all 3 meals each day, plus a morning and evening snack. The only snack not included is afternoon tuck, when a variety of snacks and drinks are available to purchase; all proceeds from tuck go to the Alison Stewart-Patterson fund, to help campers who can’t afford to pay the full camp fee.</span></p>
<p><strong>Is the food actually good? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">YES! Most meals include a few options, so even the pickiest eaters should be satisfied!</span></p>
<p><strong>I have allergies/dietary restrictions; can these be accommodated?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Yes, Camp Tamarack will do as much as possible to accommodate allergies and dietary restrictions. The kitchen staff at Tamarack are used to dealing with different allergies and dietary needs throughout the summer, so they should be able to keep you well fed through the week. In addition, the camp kitchen is a nut-free facility, so those with nut allergies should not need to worry. If you have dietary needs please note them on your registration form, or contact the registrar to discuss your needs further. If you have very severe food allergies or multiple dietary restrictions and wish to bring some of your own food, a fridge is available in the dining hall for storage; just make sure everything is very clearly labeled with your name.</span></p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1duqtojbu5"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Accommodations and Camp Site</span></h2>
<p><strong>What are the cabins like? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are several different styles of cabins at Camp Tamarack. Most of the cabins available are large dormitory-style units that would usually sleep about 16 campers (per side) on bunk beds during Tamarack’s regular summer program. We usually assign one family to each side of these cabins so there’s plenty of space. Most of these larger cabins do have a wall to divide each side, but some of the older cabins may not; if there’s no dividing wall we try to be mindful of assigning those cabins to families who either know each other or have asked to share a large cabin together. All of the cabins have electricity, and some of these larger cabins have toilets and sinks as well.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In addition to the dormitory-style cabins, there are also smaller cabins available that are used by Tamarack staff through most of the summer. These cabins range from 2 – 6 person cabins with bunk beds to cabins with a single or double bed that only sleep 1 – 2 people. All of these cabins have electricity, as well as a variety of potential bathroom set ups: some of these cabins have a toilet and sink, some have a full bathroom with shower, and some have neither. These cabins are usually assigned to couples or campers who come to PMC without other immediate family members.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is also a site for any campers who wish to bring their own tent or trailer for the week, but please note there are no service hookups available.</span></p>
<p><strong>Do I have to stay with my family?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> If you’re under the age of 13 (and won’t turn 13 before the end of the calendar year), then yes, you will need to stay with the parent or guardian who is with you at camp. For campers aged 13 – 19 we have male and female teen cabins available. For campers 18 and older, male and female young adults cabins are also available.</span></p>
<p><strong>What if my cabin doesn’t have a washroom or shower? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are washrooms and shower houses in several locations across the camp site, so no one should have to go far to find facilities. Shower houses have been renovated in recent years to provide single person shower stalls and changing spaces.</span></p>
<p><strong>Is the site accessible? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Camp Tamarack site is spread out and there is a fair amount of walking required. That being said, many campers bring their bicycles to get around more quickly, and campers with mobility issues do sometimes chose to drive themselves from one end of the site to the other.</span></p>
<p><strong>What other amenities are available at Camp Tamarack? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">In addition to the sleeping cabins and dining hall, Camp Tamarack has multiple program buildings that PMC uses for our workshops and morning and evening programs. The camp site also has a large beach front and swimming dock, soccer and baseball fields, and plenty of natural space to enjoy.</span></p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1duqto2in4"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Program</span></h2>
<p><strong>Do I have to take a workshop in every period?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Absolutely not! Some campers like to sign up for 5 workshops and have a full day, other campers take just a few of their favourite workshops, and some campers come just to enjoy being in the natural setting and spending time with friends and family. It’s entirely up to you how many workshops you want to take.</span></p>
<p><strong>Can I take different workshops on different days?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> No, unless a workshop is specifically organized as a “drop in” (like crafts), most of the workshops offered are designed to build each day, so dropping in for just one day is discouraged. Of course, if you sign up for a workshop and find that it isn’t the right fit after one or two days don’t force yourself to stay; this just means you’ll end up with a free period, which isn’t always the worst thing!</span></p>
<p><strong>What about programming for kids? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are lots of options for our younger campers. Each morning children’s choir and children’s games are available (usually for ages 6 – 12), and in the afternoon there are a number of beginner-level workshops, crafts, and swimming to keep everyone busy. For our youngest campers (up to age 5) a program is available through the morning with music, games, and other activities.</span></p>
<p><strong>Do I have to participate in the camp-wide activities?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> We encourage all campers to fully participate in order to get the full PMC experience and integrate into our community, but attendance at activities like devotions and evening program is not mandatory. If you chose not to attend a camp-wide scheduled activity we do ask that you not create a disruption for those who are taking part.</span></p>
<p><strong>I’m not Presbyterian; is that okay?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> YES! PMC is a welcoming environment for members of any faith, campers who might be questioning their faith, or campers who do not have any religious affiliation. Our camp is Christ-centered, and there are religious aspects to every day at camp, but this doesn’t preclude anyone from coming to PMC.  We have some traditions that aren’t strictly Presbyterian, but if you’re new to camp or not familiar we are happy to fill you in!</span></p>
<p><strong>Someone in my family has special needs; can they still come to camp? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Absolutely. PMC has had several campers with various special needs and they have always been included in our community. If a camper has special needs that require assistance (such as a full-time caregiver) they will need to bring someone to camp with them to help, and that person will need to register and pay for PMC; bursary help may be available to help cover the cost of a care-giver for a camper with special needs.</span></p>
<p><strong>Is the camp LGBTQ-friendly? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Yes. Everyone is welcome at camp, we are completely inclusive. We also ensure that a gender-neutral washroom and showers are available.</span></p>
<p><strong>I don’t know if my musical skills are good enough; should I come to camp? </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">We would love to have you at PMC, no matter your musical skill level. We have campers who are professional musicians, music teachers, and choir directors, campers who are just learning to read music or have picked up an instrument for the first time, and campers who can’t carry a tune but love listening to music and being in a musical environment. All are welcome and all have a place at PMC. While most of our workshops are music-focused we do have several options every day that are non-musical as well, so don’t let this stop you from coming! For our musical workshops we offer a variety of skill levels, so everyone from beginners to advanced musicians will have somewhere that they fit in.</span></p>
<p><strong>I found PMC online and want to come, but I won’t know anyone! </strong><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not to toot our own horns, but we are very welcoming! Everyone was a new camper at one time, whether they came with a parent or friend or just thought PMC sounded great and came by themselves. There’s a place for everyone at camp, and new campers have always found a group to socialize with.</span></p>
<p><strong>Is there any financial assistance available?</strong><span style="font-weight: 400;"> We have 2 bursary funds available to help campers who need financial assistance. The Alison Stewart-Patterson fund offers a bursary to cover about half of the camper fees for any camper who is not able to pay the full amount. The Tom Gemmell Bursary fund is available to cover the camper fees of one member of the clergy or certified student, and one music director each year. More information about these funds, as well as guidance on how to apply, is available on the <a href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/register.html">registration page</a>.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Blog</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/blog.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/blog.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-08T16:09:44-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    We've recently started a community blog. A blog can have many valuable aspects, but our initial&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>We've recently started a community blog. A blog can have many valuable aspects, but our initial focus is how it can serve potential campers. In particular, we want to give deeper insight into the community for people who are considering going to camp for the first time. A listing of blog posts follows.</p>
<p><a href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/my-experience-as-a-new-camper-at-presbyterian-music-camp.html">My Experience as a New Camper - Cynthia McMinn</a></p>
<p><a href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/musical-experiences.html">20 Years of Musical Experiences - Bradley Audet</a></p>
<p><a href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/living-and-rejoicing-in-christian-community.html">Living and Rejoicing in Christian Community - Marilyn Broadhead</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>20 Years of Musical Experiences</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/musical-experiences.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/musical-experiences.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-08T16:09:08-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I’ve been coming to Presbyterian Music Camp (PMC) for 20 years. Given that I am&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I’ve been coming to Presbyterian Music Camp (PMC) for 20 years. Given that I am 21 years old, you might deduce that I’ve been coming to this wonderful place for my whole life. My non-camp friends often ask, “why do you keep going back?” After all, “summer camp” tends to carry a childish connotation and, by definition, I am no longer a child.  There are many reasons why I keep coming back to camp each year. I’ll just touch on one of them here.</p>
<p>PMC is a fantastic place to grow as a musician, regardless of your age or playing ability. It is filled with the most supportive people I’ve ever met, and for that reason it’s a safe place to try new things without fear of failure and ridicule. My years at camp have been defined by a series of instances where I threw myself into something I knew nothing about and came out with a new passion. To my memory, the first of these instances was when I joined the concert band not one month after first picking up the flute. I could barely play a scale, but for some reason my 10-year-old self decided to join an ensemble comprising mostly of skilled musicians with several years’ (if not decades) experience on their instruments. However, before I could feel overwhelmed by the piece of music set before me, I was introduced to a much more talented flutist who I later learned was a music teacher by profession. She helped me get through my first week of concert band, and I left camp that year determined to come back the following year able to hold my own in the concert band.</p>
<p>A couple of years later, as a teen, I joined the jazz band, where I was confronted with an equally daunting challenge: improvisation. Luckily, as with concert band, I wasn’t without guidance. Karl and Brennan, the workshop leaders, were both seemingly virtuosic in their improvisation skills and also incredibly patient as I came to understand concepts like the blues scale and the twelve-bar blues. Jazz band became a staple of my PMC experience for several years after, which made me a much more confident and creative musician. Also, I don’t know anyone else outside of music camp who has the opportunity to swap solos with professional jazz musicians, which is rad.</p>
<p>Of course, there’s also an abundance of music that happens outside of daily workshops- music camp is an opportunity to try out any musical ideas that have come to you during the year. In recent years, some friends and I have formed a woodwind ensemble. It’s the only time in the year that I get to play classical and baroque chamber music, and I cherish it. Me and my older sister are even able to overcome our differences and sing together sometimes. Sometimes.</p>
<p>My musical experiences at camp have been both incredibly unique and commonplace. They’ve been unique in the sense that there is no other place in the world where I have found such a compassionate and talented group of people who are willing to share their ideas and passion with you. They’ve been commonplace in the sense that when at camp, I see other people, young and old, Christian and atheist, sharing similar formative experiences.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>My Experience as a New Camper</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/my-experience-as-a-new-camper-at-presbyterian-music-camp.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/my-experience-as-a-new-camper-at-presbyterian-music-camp.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-08T16:11:54-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I first discovered Presbyterian Music Camp when my daughter attended with her best friend and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div>I first discovered Presbyterian Music Camp when my daughter attended with her best friend and their family one summer. She came home with stories, pictures, and videos of musical variety night, final concert, and exploring in the woods. We didn’t immediately go back as a family, but a couple of years later three of us attended camp together. We stayed in a big cabin with our friends who had been going to camp for years. The children fit in right away with a group of other campers their ages and found workshops and activities they wanted to do or just hung out together.  </div>
<div> </div>
<div>It was intimidating for me at first. All those people! And everyone seemed to know everyone and had been at camp forever. Right away though, there was an icebreaker activity and the circle and flame ceremony to open the camp. People were really friendly and already I started to feel welcome.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>There were so many different workshops that it was hard to decide on which ones to attend. I found four that I wanted to try but kept one time slot free for some time for reflection and to get away from all the activity.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>I had a Guardian Angel who looked out for me as I found my way around camp, who introduced me to people and helped me get into the flow of camp. Up in the morning for breakfast, then gather up my things and head off to Holy Motion and Worship, and then on to the first workshop of the day. It was a bit intimidating the amount of musical talent around but then I realized that there was a huge range of abilities and everyone was welcoming and accepting of whatever talents people had.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>There were breaks during the day that made it possible to get from workshops to snack or lunch and provided a bit of time to relax or practice all the music we were learning. Just getting from one location to the next was great exercise. So much walking and an opportunity to talk to different people on the way.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>The approach to the workshops was not something I was used to. In many cases we were handed several pieces of music and we were expected to be able to perform them by the end of the week or sooner! In some cases I was learning new instruments like the ukulele as well. I have to admit that was pretty overwhelming but everyone seemed to take it in stride. And amazingly the performances happened and we were all pretty ready and they sounded good!</div>
<div> </div>
<div>Evenings were busy as well - there was a campfire sing along, variety night, coffee house and then generally people got together somewhere after to socialize. I did try to pace myself - I didn’t want to miss out on all the great activities during the day from being too tired!</div>
<div> </div>
<div>It was a whirlwind of a week and yet I came away relaxed, refreshed and happy. The combination of the setting, the people, the spirituality and the music is something extraordinary and worth going back every year to experience.</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2018</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/2018.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/2018.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-09T20:39:31-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    ThemeSeeing the Forest Through the Trees Seeing the big picture can be a daily challenge&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="mcetoc_1drmn0ms60">Theme</h2>
<p id="mcetoc_1drmn0qm61">Seeing the Forest Through the Trees</p>
<p>Seeing the big picture can be a daily challenge for many of us, when faced with our own individual realities. Together we CAN learn to see the forest through the trees by taking time out for: community in family; suffering and celebration; and growth through discipline. By taking time to step away from routines and to search for purpose, we can make space for God in our lives. Be prepared to challenge and nurture your body, soul, mind and spirit through music, song, worship and wonder!</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1drmn1vl72">Schedules</h2>
<p><a href="pmc-week-schedule-2018.pdf">week</a></p>
<p><a href="2018 PMC Schedule.pdf">workshops</a></p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1drmnb6dn0">Other Materials</h2>
<p><a href="Music Camp Handbook 2018.pdf">handbook</a></p>
<p><a href="Packing List 2018.pdf">packing list</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>2019</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/2019.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/2019.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-09T21:06:44-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    ThemeGrace Notes – Accents of Love for a Hurting World A beautiful piece of music&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="mcetoc_1drmmlldt0">Theme</h2>
<p>Grace Notes – Accents of Love for a Hurting World</p>
<p dir="ltr">A beautiful piece of music may have grace notes written throughout. When you first learn the piece, you are likely to skip the grace notes, and the music still sounds complete, even without them. But once you know the music better, you realise the composer meant the music to be played with the grace notes included. So you practise with them, and suddenly you realise you had been missing out on a whole other dimension to the music – the grace notes add depth, colour and meaning to the piece, and it is played the way it was meant to be played. So it is with our lives. We can live our lives well enough without ever letting grace in. But God the composer intended our lives to be filled with grace. Once you discover God’s grace and get to know the meaning God has for your life – the purpose of the composer – your life can become deeper and fuller, more as it was meant to be lived, echoing into eternity.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Come and join us by the trees and the lake, in beautiful Muskoka, and hear the music of grace – God’s accents of love for a hurting world – speak to your soul.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1drmmnuu95">Schedules</h2>
<p><a href="pmc week schedule 2019.pdf">week</a></p>
<p><a href="2019 PMC Schedule.pdf">workshops</a></p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1drmmn4901">Other Materials</h2>
<p><a href="Music Camp Handbook 2019.pdf">handbook</a></p>
<p><a href="Packing List 2019.pdf">packing list</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Past Years</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/past-years.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/past-years.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-09T19:55:32-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    2019scheduleworkshops
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h2 id="mcetoc_1drmkoup60">2019</h2>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1drmkqpjk2">schedule</h3>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1drmkqnie1">workshops</h3>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>This Year</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/this-year.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/this-year.html</id>

        <updated>2019-12-09T19:41:11-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    PMC 2020 takes place August 23rd to 30th! New campers receive a 50% discount this&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="align-center">PMC 2020 takes place August 23rd to 30th!</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1drmjpt7g2">New Camper Promo</h2>
<p>New campers receive a 50% discount this year! More information will follow.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Tom Gemmell Bursary Application Process</title>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Eisner</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/tom-gemmell-bursary-application.html"/>
        <id>https://presbyterian-music-camp.github.io/website/tom-gemmell-bursary-application.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-07T18:02:01-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Complete an application.Send the application to the convener by May 15th.The camp committee will anonymously review&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <ol>
<li>Complete an <a href="TG_application_v4.docx">application</a>.</li>
<li>Send the application to the convener by <strong>May 15th</strong>.</li>
<li>The camp committee will anonymously review all the Tom Gemmell bursary requests we received up to May 15th, and allocate funds. You should hear from us about funding by May 31st.</li>
<li>If additional campers will accompany you to camp (e.g., family members) and they require bursary support, you may apply for an ASP bursary for these campers. These campers will pay the early bird fee if they register by June 30.</li>
<li>If you are unable to attend camp for any reason, please let us know as soon as possible so that we can consider reallocating your bursary.</li>
<li>The camp committee may choose to consider requests received between May 15th and July 31st, if funding permits. The camp committee will not consider any requests received after July 31st.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you have any questions about the Tom Gemmell Fund, please send an email to the convener at <a href="mailto:presbyterianmusiccamp@gmail.com">presbyterianmusiccamp@gmail.com</a>.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
